Finding Aid for the Abiko Family Papers, ca. 1890-1944 LSC.1690
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Incoming Family Correspondence to Abiko Yonako
  - From Friends and Associates
    - Osawa M. [characters]., 5 Letters. (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - (August 1, [????]). (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - (November 9, [????]). (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - (December 10, [????]). (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - (December 18, [????]). (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Sagitani Seiichi, Nichibei Shimbun Tokyo Correspondent, 1936-1941.; 10 Letters. (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (June 21 [????]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (July 5, [????]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (January 23, [1936]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (December 17, [1937?]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (July 4, [1939]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - [1939?]. (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (April 10 [1941]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (June 22, [1941]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (September 14, [1941]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - (October 14, [1941]). (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Yamanaka Chuji & Sen [characters], Former Nichibei Shimbun Employee & Wife, 1921-1922; 4 Letters. (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - (November 29, [1921]). (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - (February 24, [1922?]). (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - (March 31, [1922]). (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - (April 26, [1922]). (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Other Miscellaneous Japanese Correspondence
    - Tsuda & Suto Families, 1905-1941.; 6 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Abiko Family, 1915-1935.; 5 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Nichibei Shimbun, 1935-1940; 6 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, 1915.; 3 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Kaigai Doho Chuokai [characters] (Overseas Japanese Association), 1941.; 3 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Hayashi Shichibe [characters], 1914-1915.; 5 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Congratulatory Messages, 1899-1941.; 12 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Announcements & Invitations, 1912-1941.; 14 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Postcards, 1908-1937.; 7 items. (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Bon Voyage Letters., 3 Letters. (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Greeting Letters and Postcards, 1910-1941.; 21 items. (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Thank You Notes, 1908-1919.; 17 items. (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Thank You Notes, 1920-1931.; 13 items. (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Thank You Notes, 1935-1941.; 15 items. (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Letters & Postcards from Returnees to Japan, 1915-1941.; 20 items. (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1897-1907.; 7 items. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Letters & Postcard, 1910-1914.; 10 items. (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Letters & Postcard, 1915-1918.; 12 items. (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1919-1921.; 8 items. (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1922-1923.; 6 items. (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1930-1931.; 5 items. (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1932-1933.; 3 items. (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1936-1939.; 5 items. (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous Letters & Postcards, 1940.; 6 items. (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1941.; 7 items. (Box 25, Folder 10)
- Incoming Correspondence in English
  - Ella Beach, Friend, 1902-1921; 15 Letters & 2 Postcards
    - (September 28, 1902)., Page missing. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (February 8, 1903)., Enclosure, Valentine card. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (February 18, [1907]). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - [April 30, 1907]. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (October 29, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (December 3, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - [December 6, 1907]., Postcard. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (December 12, 1907)., Enclosure, Newspaper clipping. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - [December 15, 1907]., Postcard. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - [1907?]. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (February 7, 1909). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (February 19, 1909). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (June 6, 1909). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (January 23, [1910]. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (November 27, 1921). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (December 7, 1921). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - (December 22, [????]). (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Agnes Celli (Bolds), Friend, 1907-1909.; 4 Letters & 1 Postcard. (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - (December 5, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - (December 16, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - (July 4, 1908)., Postcard. (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - (October 4, 1908). (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - (February 24, 1909). (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Joseph Elkinton, Friend & Brother of Mary R.E. Nitobe, , 1907-1909.; 8 Letters. (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (April 2, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (April 17, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (June 10, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (August 12, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (November 21, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (January 1, 1908). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (February 17, 1909). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - (July 23, 1909). (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Joseph Elkinton, 1913-1916; 10 Letters. (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (February 13, 1913). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - [October 18, 1913]. (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (May 13, 1914). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (February 12, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (May 18, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (August 27, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (September 21, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (December 30, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - [1915?]. (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - (December 30, 1916). (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Sara W. Elkinton, Wife of Joseph Elkinton, 1915-1927.; 7 Letters. (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - (August 10, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - (September 26, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - (December 29, 1916). (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - (November 14, 1921). (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - (November 30, 1921). (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - (December 5, 1921). (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - (October 7, 1927). (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Anna C. Hartshorne, Tsuda College Patron & Trustee, 1915-1931.; 5 Letters. (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - (February 24, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - (July 30, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - (August 6, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - (March 23, 1927). (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - (August 14, 1931). (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Mary R. Elkinton Nitobe, Friend & Wife of Nitobe Inazo, 1907-1937.; 7 Letters, 1 Christmas Card, & 2 Postcards. (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (January 22, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (May 2, 1907). (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (January 2, 1909)., Postcard. (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - [January 31, 1911]., Postcard. (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (December 6, 1913)., Christmas Card. (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (April 21, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (November 29, 1915). (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (September 13, 1917). (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (October 21, 1932). (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - (June 8, 1937). (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - May Wright Sewall, Chairperson, International Conference of Women Workers, 1915.; 10 Letters. (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Mary Verg, Friend, 1904-1914.; 13 Letters & 1 Card. (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - (August 31, [1904]. (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - (April 29, [1906]). (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - (January 24, [1907]). (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - [1907]. (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - (January 16, [1908]). (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - (February 4, [1909?]). (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - (April 29, [1912]). (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - [November 10, 1913]. (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - [May 6, 1914]. (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - (August 15, [????]). (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - 2 Undatable Letter & 2 Undatable Cards. (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Hana Yamada, Nisei, 1935-1940.; 5 Letters. (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - [1935]. (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - (February 15, 1936). (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - (May 31, 1936). (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - (April 11, 1940). (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - (September 27, 1940). (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - K. Loldaini, Friend., 2 French Letters. (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - [August 19, 1908]. (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - (November 28, 1908). (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - 14 Meeting Notices and Invitations, 1910-1919. (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - 14 Meeting Notices and Invitations, 1920-1923. (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - 16 Thank You Letters, 1906-1919. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - 16 Thank You Letters, 1921-1941. (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - 8 Greeting Letters & Postcards, 1907-1922. (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - 9 Greeting Letters & Cards, 1931-1941. (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - 10 Wedding Congratulation Letters, 1909. (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - 5 Birth Congratulation Letters, 1910. (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - 7 Notices of Absence, 1916-1940. (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - 7 Announcement Letters, 1912-1934. (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - 4 Bon Voyage Letters, 1907. (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - 5 Letters on Selection of Japanese Female Students to Study in America, 1914-1922. (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - 4 Letters on the Kanto Earthquake., 1923 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - 12 Miscellaneous Letters, 1906-1915. (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - 8 Miscellaneous Letters, 1916-1920. (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - 12 Miscellaneous Letters, 1920-1922. (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - 11 Miscellaneous Letters, 1930-1931. (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - 11 Miscellaneous Letters, 1932-1937. (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - 3 Miscellaneous Letters, 1940. (Box 29, Folder 6)
- Nichibei Shimbun Kengakudan
  - Kengakudan Scrapbook, 1925. (Box 30, Folder 1)
    (See also oversize items no.1 & no.2)
  - Kengakudan Scrapbook, 1926. (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Nichibei Shimbun English Clippings, April 3-July 29, 1925. (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Abiko Yonako to Abiko Kyutaro, 1925-1926.; 5 Letters & 3 Postcards. (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - (April 3, [1925]). (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - (April 5, [1925]). (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - (April 11, [1925]). (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - [March 1926].. (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - (April 5, 1926). (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - (April 10, 1926)., Postcard. (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - (April 14, 1926)., Postcard. (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - (May 11, [1926])., Postcard. (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Yorokobino Kotoba [characters], 3 Congratulatory Poems by Chigusa Shisui [characters]. (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings & speech texts. (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - 12 Group & Individual Photographs. (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - 10 Group & Individual Photographs. (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Kengakudan Photo Album, 1925. (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Kengakudan Photo Album, 1925. (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Kengakudan Photo Album, 1926. (Box 32, Folder 3)
- Tsuda College Emergency Committee
  (see also Box 35, Folder 4).
  - California Branch Balance Sheets, November 17, 1924-December 27, 1926. (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - California Branch Correspondence Files, November 17, 1924-Aug. 25, 1925.; 63 items. (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - California Branch Correspondence Files, November 17, 1924-July 29, 1925.; 25 items. (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Abiko Yonako Correspondence with John A. McGregor, Treasurer, California Branch., 4 items. (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - (March 3, 1927). (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - (December 31, 1927),., Enclosures, 2 Telegrams. (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - (February 15, 1928)., Enclosures, 2 Letters exchanged between John A. McGregor & Sidney M. Ehrman. (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - (February 21, 1928). (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Abiko Yonako Correspondence with Narcissa Cox Vanderlip, New York branch., 7 items. (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - (March 3, 1925). (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - (October 3, 1927). (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - (January 13, 1928)., Telegram. (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - (January 24, 1928)., Telegram. (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - (August 15, [1928]). (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - (October 7, 1929). (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Undatable. (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Other Correspondence of Abiko Yonako, 1924-1929.; 10 items. (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Letters of Introduction of Abiko Yonako., 4 copies. (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Tsuda College Emergency Committee Pamphlets., 21 items. (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Tsuda College Emergency Committee Pamphlets., 12 items. (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Tsuda College Postcards., 9 items. (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Materials. (Box 33, Folder 11)
- Abiko Kyutaro Personal Memorabilia
  - 3 Autobiographical Notes & Autobiographical Letter,, to Uncle., (Jan 9, 1906) (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - 2 Diaries, 1932. (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Materials on the Japanese Government Award of the 5th Order of the Sacred Treasure, 1928.; 4 items. (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Materials on the Yamato and Cortez Colonies., 4 items. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - American Land and Produce Company, Loan Agreement. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Beikoku Kashu Yamato Shokuminchi Jijo, [characters], 1909?. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Cortez Colony land purchase financial note. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Partial list of settlers in Livingston and Cressey. (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Materials., 14 items. (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Letters Pertaining to the Nichibei Shimbun 1931 Strike., 5 items. (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Letters of Sympathy, 1932.; 12 items. (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Incoming Japanese Correspondence, 1909-1927.; 12 Letters. (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Incoming Japanese Correspondence, 1931.; 7 Letters. (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Incoming Japanese Correspondence, 1932-1933.; 8 Letters (4 undatable). (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Incoming English Correspondence, 1908-1936.; 10 Letters & 2 Postcards. (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Documents on the Death of Abiko Kyutaro. (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - Record of Funeral Gifts. (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Record of Donation for Monument. (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Former Nichibei Shimbun Employee Autograph Book,, with photo., 1933 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Tsuda College Emergency Committee, California Branch Minutes, November 13, 1924-June. 16, 1925. (Box 35, Folder 4)
- Nichibei Shimbun Documents
  - Legal Briefs, 1938.; 11 items. (Box 36, Folder 1)
    (See also oversize item no.3).
  - Legal Briefs, 1937-1938.; 4 items. (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Documents on 1937-1938 Law Suit., 7 items. (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Documents on Strike., 1931; 4 items. (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Financial Records, 1932-1942.; 7 items. (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Documents. (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, April 29, 1932-May 26, 1941. (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Financial Journal, October 1941-May 1942. (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Employee Salary Record, March 1941-May 1942. (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Business Record, 1937-1942. (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Advertisement & Subscription Income Record, April-June 1942. (Box 38, Folder 2)
- Yasuo Abiko Personal Memorabilia
  - Umbilical Cord & Teeth. (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Diary, March 9; June 25, 28-August 6, 18; October 3, 31, 1916. (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - English Spelling Exercise Sheets. (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Math Exercise Sheets. (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Japanese Composition & Calligraphic Exercises. (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Materials., 10 items. (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Parents, 1921-1933.; 13 items. (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Incoming Letters., 10 items. (Box 39, Folder 8)
- Yasuo Abiko Nichi Bei Jiji Files
  - 442nd Regimental Combat Team., 15 items. (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Postwar Buddhist Church., 17 items. (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Nisei Notables. (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Issues of Postwar Japanese-American Newspapers., 7 items. (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Nichi Bei Jiji Materials., 6 items. (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Business Correspondence, 1946-1948.; 33 Letters. (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Business Correspondence, 1957-1972.; 33 Letters. (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 27 items. (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 43 items. (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - Japanese American Citizens League Documents. (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Evacuation Claims., 4 items. (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Committee for Return of Confiscated German and Japanese Property., 26 items. (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Japanese Christian Church Newsletters., 12 items. (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - San Francisco Japantown Redevelopment., 9 photos, 15 items, and newspaper clippings. (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Nikkei Lions Club., 17 items. (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Nisei Sports Groups., 22 items. (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Nisei Entertainers and Athletes. (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Materials., 9 items. (Box 41, Folder 9)
- Photographs
  - Baby Photo Album. (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Baby Photographs., 12 items. (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Baby Photographs., 8 items. (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Abiko Family Photographs., 57 items. (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Scenic Photographs., 12 items. (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Non-Japanese., 11 items. (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Wedding Photographs., 9 items. (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 10 items. (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 10 items. (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 20 items. (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Wedding Photographs., 5 items. (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 5 items. (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 6 items. (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 9 items. (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs., 14 items. (Box 44, Folder 5)
- Oversize Items
  - Kengakudan Photo Album, 1926. (Box 45)
  - 4 Kengakudan Photographs. (Box 45)
  - Rice paddle post card to K. Abiko, April 14, 1926. (Box 45)
  - Nichibei Shimbun Business Record, December 1940-June 1942. (Box 46)